Who's there? Who calls my name?
是谁？是谁在叫我？
It is I. Lord?
是我。
是主？
Get up and go to the great city of Nineveh, announce my judgment against it,
你起来往尼尼微大城去，向其中的居民呼喊。
because I have seen how wicked its people are.
因为他们的恶达到我面前。
Lord, that place is home to enemies, who have attacked and killed your people. They deserve your wrath.
主啊，那是仇敌住的地方，他们攻击，杀害你的百姓，就该承受你的愤怒。
They cursed your name, Lord, and do not deserve even a chance for forgiveness.
他们诅咒你的名，主啊，他们根本不配你的赦免。
Jonah.
约拿
I cannot, I will not go there.
不，我不去！
Destroy the city lord, bury it, but I beg you, leave me out of it.
主，毁灭那座城市吧，但我求你别把我牵扯进去！
Careful, Gizmo!
It's all under the control, Joy.
小心，Gizmo！
一切都在掌握之中，Joy。
Too close!
好险啊！
Can you steer on that thing?
你能驾驶那玩意儿么？
That's Gizmo's job!
Give me a break!
那是Gizmo的事！
打住吧！
Break?
No, she didn't mean...
打住？
不，她不是这意思！
I'll walk to my first class. Thank you.
那我就走着去上课了，谢谢。
I am in charge of the recycling program today.
今天我负责环保回收。
Recycling? Huh? Is this Aluminum？ Do not get any ideas!
回收哈，这是铝合金的吧？别想打我的主意！
What is this?
这是什么啊？
I'm after lunch money, not your lunch. Tuna fish?
我要的是午餐费，不是午餐！金枪鱼?
Next time I see you, I want two dollars each, got it?
下次再见到你们，每人给我两块钱，听懂了吗？
Oh, and a cookie!
外加一块曲奇
Cool bike!
好酷的车！
Someone forgot to lock up.
有人忘记锁车了。
And you're sure it was Sharon?
你确定就是沙伦？
Definitely, Principal Travis,
校长，肯定是她！
She pulls the stuff all the time. She's the one who threw my backpack into the pool last month.
她总是捣乱，上个月就是他把我的背包扔进了水池！
She's been in and out of my office all year.
这一年，她到我办公室来了不知多少次了。
Maybe this time, we can help her make another choice.
也许这一次，我们可以帮他做个不同的选择。
I don't understand. What If you and I go talk to her, give her a chance to come clean.
我们找他谈谈，给他一个承认错误的机会，怎么样？
Come clean? But she is a crock!
承认错误？但她太坏了！
Punishment might just push her further down that path.
惩罚只会让她变得越来越坏。
Meet me after school, let's try it my way first.
好了，放学后来见我，咱们先试试我的办法。
Hey joy.  What's up?
嘿 Joy，出了什么事？
I can't believe it. This school is soft on crime!
难以置信！这所学校对罪太手软了！
Sharon Mel stole a bike in broad daylight,
沙伦梅尔大白天偷了一辆自行车
and Miss Travis just wants to let her slide by or give a mercy or something.
莱维斯校长却想放她一马，说要宽容怜悯她，哼！
A girl like Sharon has to be taught a lesson.
像沙伦那样的女生，必须教训一通才行！
I am taking you to a man who is running from God,
我要带你们去见一个人，这个人逃避神，
someone who must be shown Mercy himself before he can show it to others.
他必须先得到神的怜悯和原谅，然后才能学会怜悯和原谅别人。
Where are we now? Gizmo?
我们现在在哪？Gizmo?
We don't need a /(ㄒoㄒ)/ to tell us we are on a ship, Joy!
不用扫描仪也能知道我们在一艘船上！Joy!
It gotta takes me a while to get my sea legs.
看样子我一时半会儿习惯不了海上的生活。
I get the only sea legs, you see!
伙计们看我的本领。
You there, get below before the waves knock you off the deck!
下来，小心海浪把你们卷走！
You actually heard God's voice? Yes.
你真听到神对你说话了？是的。
Telling me to go to Nineveh, a city filled with God's worst enemies.
神让我去尼尼微城，那里住着他的仇敌。
Killers of his people.
杀了许多祂的百姓。
God wanted me to warn them, he was about to pass judgment, but why warn them.
神要我警告他们，他将审判他们，可是凭什么要警告他们？
So they repent, say they are sorry, and then receive God's mercy？
说声对不起，然后得到神的怜悯？
I say, no, if Nineveh is doomed, then let it be doomed.
不，如果尼尼微注定要灭亡，就让他灭亡吧！
So you ran away from God？
所以你就躲避上帝？
Technically speaking, hiding from the all knowing deity is statistically impossible.
技术上说，躲避全知的上帝是绝对不可能的。
I'm beginning to understand that.
我也慢慢明白这点了。
Here he is, below deck!
他在甲板下面！
How can you sleep at a time like this? Get up and pray to your God.
你这沉睡的人哪，为何这样呢。起来，求告你的神，
Maybe he will pay attention to us and spare our lives.
或者神顾念我们，使我们不致灭亡。
Let us cast lots to show who cause all this trouble!
来吧，我们掣签，看看这灾临到我们是因谁的缘故。
They must be trying to see of Jonah cause the storm!
他们想看看，是不是约拿招来了暴风雨。
He is the corporate! Why has this awful storm come down on us?
原来是他，这风暴为什么临到我们？
Who are you? What's your line of work?
你是干什么的？
What country are you from? Who are your people?
你是哪一国，属哪一族的人?
I am a Hebrew, and I worship the Lord, the God of the heaven,
我是希伯来人，我敬畏耶和华，那创造沧海和地，的天上的神。
You see, it is his fault!
看到了吗，都是他的错！
He told us before that he was trying to flee from his God.
Why did you do it?
他之前说过，他在躲避他的神。
你为什么这么做？
What should we do to you to stop this storm?
我们改拿你怎么办来停止这风暴？
Throw me into the sea, and it will become calm again.
你们将我抬起来，抛在海中，海就平静了
I know that this terrible storm is all my faults.
我知道你们遭这大风，是因我的缘故。
There is gotta be another way!
一定还有别的办法的！
Guess we need to pick better friends.
下次得交好点儿的朋友。
You are friends with the Hebrew, take these three as well!
你们是这家伙的朋友吗，把这三个也扔出去
Look out, the mast is coming down!
小心！桅杆掉下来了！
Oh Lord, do not make us die for this man's sin!
主啊，别让我们因为这个人的最丧命！
And do not hold us responsible for his death, you have sent this storm upon him for your own good reasons!
别因为他的死，追究我们的责任。你让风暴临到他，有你的理由。
Throw off the boat with all of them!
把他们全都扔下去！
I am so sorry, my friends.
我很抱歉，朋友。
Don't worry about it, and see, even the storms cleared now.
别担心，嘿，快看的风暴停了。
All's well that ends well, I always say.
结果好，一切都好
Ah, Chris, I am detecting a very large creature, just three fathoms below us.
我侦侧到我们以下有一头庞大的动物正在靠近。
And I thought fish were slimy on the outside. This is unbelievable.
我以为鱼只有外面才黏糊糊的呢，真让人受不了。
Disaster follows me at every turn, I will not live through this.
灾难就一直追着我，简直活不下去了。
Jonah, I think if God wanted you dead, you would be dead.
神要你死，你肯定早死了。
I almost think he wants to save you.
但我觉得他其实是想救你。
Next time, he should just send some life preservers.
下次他最好先送些救生设备来。
You ran in the opposite direction from where God wanted you to go.
神让你往东去，可你却偏偏往西走
and it seems like he's done one thing after another to pull you back to him.
但他好像借着七二连三发生的事，叫你回到他面前。
He pursues me even now.
就是现在他也在追逐我
I cried out to you in my great trouble, Lord, and he answered me,
我遭遇患难求告耶和华，你就应允我。
I called to you from the Land of the Dead, and Lord, you heard me.
从阴间的深处呼求，你就俯听我的声音。
Feels like we're moving in a new direction. It sure does.
好像我们正在朝新的方向移动哦。的确如此。
You throw me into the ocean depths, and I sank to the heart of the sea.
你将我投下深渊，就是海的深处。
Mighty waters engulfed me, I was buried beneath your wild and stormy waves.
大水环绕我。你的波浪洪涛都漫过我身。
But you, O Lord my God snatched me from the jaws of death.
耶和华我的神阿，你却将我的性命，从坑中救出来。
As my life was slipping away. I remembered the Lord.
我心在我里面发昏的时候，我就想念耶和华。
and my earnest prayer went out to you in your holy temple.
我的祷告进入你的圣殿，达到你的面前。
Those who worship false gods turn their backs on all God's mercies.
那信奉虚无之神的人，离弃怜爱他们的主。
But I will offer sacrifices to you with songs of praise, and I will fulfill all my vows.
但我必用感谢的声音献祭与你。我所许的愿，我必偿还。
My salvation comes from the lord alone.
救恩出于耶和华。
Amazing, full terrestrial expectoration.
太棒了，海陆空超级喷吐秀。
You mean, we just got barfed up.
你的意思是，我们刚被吐出来。
Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and preach to it the message that I tell you.
你起来，往尼尼微大城去，向其中的居民宣告我所吩咐你的话。
And now to Nineveh, though they do not deserve the warning I bring.
我现在就去尼尼微，尽管他们根本不配听见我带来的警告。
Move on, you lazy beast!
快点走，你这个懒家伙！
How do you even talk to these people, Jonah?
这样的人，你怎么和他们讲话呢？
You steal from me!
偷我的东西！
People of Nineveh!
尼尼微的人呐！
Lord, my God has sent me to announce his judgment against your city, because he has seen your wickedness.
耶和华我的神派我来宣布他对尼尼微的审判，因为他已经看到你们的罪恶。
Forty days from now, nineveh will be destroyed.
再过40天，你们就要毁灭了。
Sure not going to make any friends delivering that kind of message.
传达这样的消息，他肯定交不到朋友了。
I do not think making friends is the mission God has in the mind for him.
我想上帝给约拿的使命不是为了交朋友
Jonah says these people are his enemies, but they're people, too.
约拿说，这些人是他的仇敌，可是他们也同样是人呢
Oh, heed me, Nineveh's, your days are drawing to a close.
哦，听着，尼尼微人，你们的日子快到头了。
Nineveh will be destroyed by a heavenly force so mighty, the likes of which its citizens have never seen.
尼尼微将被属天的力量摧毁，这力量无比强大，这里的居民从未见过。
Not in all the enemies of Syria has ever fought combined.
他比你们所有的敌人加起来的力量还要强大
Jonah. If God has shown you so much mercy, yes, saving you from that storm.
神已经怜悯原谅了你。是啊。他就你脱离了暴风雨。
And then getting you out of the belly of that giant fish,
然后又让你从大鱼的肚子里出来
why wouldn't he show the same kind of mercy to the Nineveh's, I mean,
那他为什么就不能同样怜悯原谅尼尼微人呢？
If they're willing to change.
如果他们愿意改变的话。
Do not even speak those words, these people do not deserve God's forgiveness.
你们别再说了 这些人就是不配得到神的赦免和怜悯
Even if we ask for it with all our hearts?
即使我们真心的认罪悔改也不行么？
Prophet, we have heard your words.
先知，我们听到了你的话。
We are fasting and have put on this sackcloth.
我们禁食，又穿上麻布衣服。
We have sat in ashes to show all that we are asking forgiveness.
我们坐在灰中，畏罪哀痛，都是为了寻求赦免。
It is amazing. Your words have been heard by all of Miniva, from the greatest to the least of us.
真是奇妙，尼尼微人，无论尊卑老少都听到了您的话。
This cannot be.
这不可能！
Even the king has heard your words.
连国王都听到了你的话
This day, I proclaim to the city of Ninava.
今天，我要向尼尼微全城下令。
No one, not even the animals from your herds and flocks, may eat or drink anything at all.
人不可尝什么，牲畜，牛羊不可吃草，也不可喝水。
People and animals alike must wear garments of mourning, and everyone must pray earnestly to God.
人与牲畜都当披上麻布，人要恳切求告神。
They must turn from their evil ways and stop all their violence.
各人回头离开所行的恶道，丢弃手中的强暴。
Who can tell? Perhaps even yet god will change his mind and hold back his fierce anger from destroying us?
或者神转意后悔，不发烈怒，使我们不致灭亡，也未可知。
Jonah sure seems upset about something.
约拿好像还在为什么生气哦。
Well, it's been forty days and everyone is repented.
已经40天了，所有人都归改了。
Didn't I say before I left home that you would do this, lord, that is why I ran away to Tarshish?
耶和华阿，我在本国的时候，岂不是这样说吗。所以我急速逃往他施去。
I knew that you were a merciful and compassionate God, slow to get angry and filled with unfailing love.
我知道你是有恩典，有怜悯的神，不轻易发怒，有丰盛的慈爱，
You are eager to turn back from destroying people. Oh, I'd rather be dead than alive.
并且后悔不降所说的灾，耶和华阿，现在求你取我的命吧。因为我死了比活着还好。
I have done what the Lord asked of me.
我已经按照神所吩咐的做了。
And he gives me this plant to shade my head and provides me comfort.
他给了我这颗蓖麻遮荫， 我知道他是来安慰我。
But then he shows the same mercy to all the sinners of Nineveh.
可他也同样怜悯尼尼微城的那些罪人们。
Where is the justice in that?
这哪里是公义的呢？
I always thought that when someone does something wrong, they should be punished,
我从前总认为如果别人做了错事，就该受到惩罚。
but when I do the wrong thing, I'm pretty glad that God forgives,
可是当我自己犯了罪，就因神仍饶恕罪人而欢喜。
but you and I live better lives than those people.
可是你我比那些人强多了啊！
So much for shade. I'll look for some more cover.
荫凉一下子就没有了，我去找找别的地方
Is it too much to save one little plant lord? The only thing that gave me comfort.
主啊，就这么一颗蓖麻活下来很难吗，这是唯一能安慰我的东西啊
Is it right for you to be angry about a plant?
你因这棵蓖麻发怒合乎理吗？
You have had pity on the plant for which you have not labored, nor made it grow.
这蓖麻不是你栽种的，也不是你培养的。
It came up in a night and perished in a night.
一夜发生，一夜乾死，你尚且爱惜。
And should I not pity Nineveh.
何况这尼尼微大城
That great city in which are more than 120 thousand persons who cannot discern between their right hand and their left.
其中不能分辨左手右手的有十二万多人
If I accept mercy from God.
如果我希望神原谅我
I have to be willing to give it to others,
那我也应该去原谅别人
even Sharon Myers.
甚至是沙罗梅尔？
Excuse me, guys, I think I have an appointment to keep.
抱歉，伙伴们，我要遵守一个约定。
So we wondered if you'd heard anything about a stolen bike.
你听说了么，有人丢了一辆自行车
Oh, you want my help. Whoever took it may have just made a mistake.
嗯。你们想让我帮忙吗？ 不管是谁拿的，都可能是弄错了。
They still have time to do the right thing.
但他们仍然有改正的机会
I-I took it, I don't know why I did it. It was stupid and
我拿的，我不知道为什么要那么做，真是太愚蠢了。
I'm sorry.
对不起
That took guts, Sharon, I'm not going to punish you
这是个勇敢的决定，Sharon，我不会惩罚你的
if you can help us return the bike to its rightful.
可我需要你帮忙把自行车还给他的主人
I guess I can do that.
没问题
God led a whole city off the hook, I think I can give Shalom Meir a second chance.
连整座城的人神都能赦免，我想我也可以再给沙伦梅尔一次机会。
Time to go home. I'll walk this time, I've got some thinking to deal,
该回家了，这次我要走着回去，我要思考些事
Suit yourself, Joy, you don't know what you're missing.
随你了，错过可别后悔哦！
I am done with it! I am walking with Joy!
够了！我要和Joy一起走！
Walking is good! I like walking, walking is good, I do it all the time.
我喜欢走路。走路挺好。
Jesus you died upon the cross
And rose again to save the lost
Forgive me now of all my sin
Come be my savior, Lord and friend
Change my life and make it new
And help me Lord to live for you